Okay, moving on to joint, a few basic points before we begin.
The first is that a joint is a connection between two bones.
We have solid joints, and solid joints are tightly connected,
and the purpose of solid joints is to provide structural strength between two bones.
And then we have synovial joints, and synovial joints have a joint space that allow for motion.
The rest of this talk is really going to focus on the synovial joints.
Now let's go back and remind ourselves of the anatomy of the joint.
So imagine that these are two bones that need to move against each other.
Remember that each of these bones would, on its surface, have something called an articular cartilage.
So this would be the articular cartilage here and articular cartilage here.
And the purpose of this cartilage is to allow for movement against these two bones.
Remember that the cartilage is made of type 2 collagen, and that's particularly high yield.
Of course, this joint would be surrounded by a joint capsule.
So we can imagine that this is the joint capsule here and joint capsule here.
And then the inner lining of that joint capsule would be lined by something called synovium.
So all of this, for example, would represent synovium.
And the purpose of synovium is to secrete a fluid that is rich in hyaluronic acid.
And it's that hyaluronic acid that then goes into the joint space and helps to further lubricate the joint space.
So again, just three things, bone, cartilage, and then the synovium, which secrete synovial fluid.
Now with that background, we can then go into each of the disorders.
The first disorder is degenerative joint disease.
This is when you get progressive degeneration of the articular cartilage.
Recall that the articular cartilage was that layer that was sitting on top of the bone
that was going to help for movement between the bones.
Now it's important to note that degenerative joint disease is a wear and tear disease.
Once you understand that, everything else is downhill.
The major risk factor is going to be age.
Of course, if it's wear and tear, the longer you bang on it, the more likely you are to get the disease.
And additional risk factors include obesity.
The more weight you put on the joint, the more likely you are to wear it down.
And trauma.
If a joint is deformed because of trauma or if a joint is heavily damaged because of trauma,
then it can also degenerate.
Degenerative joint disease affects a limited number of joints.
And it usually involves the hips, the lower lumbar spine, the knees, and the DIP and PIP of the fingers.
That's particularly high yield.
Both the DIP and the PIP will be involved.
Degenerative joint disease classically presents as joint stiffness in the morning that worsens during the day.
And this worsens during the day is particularly important.
The idea here is that when patients go to sleep at night, the joint gets rest.
When they wake up, they feel a little bit stiff.
However, when they begin to use the joint, the more they wear and tear it, the more they're going to begin to feel the pain.
And so this will worsen during the day, and that's particularly high yield.
The pathologic hallmark of degenerative joint disease is disruption of the cartilage that lines the articular surface.
Again, here's the bone, and then you've got this articular surface here.
And this cartilage will become disrupted.
Now, when this cartilage becomes disrupted, a few things will happen.
Number one, some of these fragments of cartilage will actually fall off into the joint space, and we call those joint mice.
Number two, as the cartilage is completely worn away, then bone will be rubbing against bone, up here for example.
And that will result in ebernation or polishing of the bone.
So you'll get ebernation of the subchondral bone.
Number three is that as you get bone rubbing against bone, you're going to get some reactive bony outgrowths.
And those are called osteophytes.
And so you'll see development of osteophytes in the area of damage as well.
Now, particularly high yield, the osteophytes classically arise in the DIP and PIP joints of the fingers.
And when this occurs, the patients get enlargement and thickening of the DIP and PIP joints.
And those are called Herberdin and Bouchard nodes.
And here's a picture highlighting disruption of the cartilage that lines the articular surface.
So this would be the joint space here.
Now, this should have been the normal cartilage coming across like this.
And you can clearly see that this cartilage is disrupted.
Now, what will eventually happen is that bone here, for example, will rub against bone here from the other side of the joint, for example.
This will result in polishing of the bone, giving you ebernation.
And will also eventually result in these bony outgrowths or osteophytes, which could result in enlargement or thickening of the joint.
Rheumatoid arthritis is a chronic systemic autoimmune disease.
It's more commonly seen in middle-aged women.
That's consistent with it being autoimmune.
And it's associated with HLA-DR4.
This is particularly high yield for board exam purposes.
Now, although it's a systemic disease, the characteristic is really involvement of the joints, hence the term rheumatoid arthritis.
And the hallmark is synovitis, or inflammation of the synovium, which leads to formation of a panis.
And a panis, basically, is inflamed granulation tissue.
This is really the highest yield point concerning this disorder.
So let's just illustrate this briefly.
Here's your bone.
And then, of course, you've got another bone forming the joint.
There's articular cartilage sitting on top of both of these.
And then there's a joint capsule.
Now, recall that the lining of the joint capsule is called synovium.
And so what's going to happen in rheumatoid arthritis is that you get a synovitis with inflammation of the synovium.
Now, when you get inflammation of the synovium, that's going to produce a thick layer of granulation tissue because of the inflammation.
Now, this granulation tissue, of course, go back to our prior lectures, contains three things.
It contains blood vessels.
It contains fibroblasts.
But it also contains myofibroblasts.
Recall that the myofibroblasts have contractile function.
And they're, of course, what causes a scar to contract.
Well, in the same way that myofibroblasts in this granulation tissue will contract.
And when they contract, a few things can happen.
Number one, you'll get fusion of the joint, which is called ankylosis.
Or number two, you can get the dragging of joints in different directions as this granulation tissue contracts.
And so that's another problem that can occur in rheumatoid arthritis where you get the movement of joints in different directions.
For example, deviations of joints.
For example, different deviations of joints.
And at the same time, because you've got this pannus taking over the articular cartilage,
you can also get destruction of the articular cartilage as well.
So this is really the hallmark.
This is the key take-home.
Synovitis with formation of a pannus.
With that in mind, let's go back and read the text.
The hallmark is synovitis, which leads to formation of a pannus.
This results in destruction of the cartilage and ankylosis of the joints.
One of the clinical hallmarks of this disorder is that you get morning stiffness that improves with activity.
The idea is that when the patient's sleeping and the joints are sitting at rest,
the inflammatory process can easily occur within the joints and begins to damage the joints.
So they wake up feeling very stiff.
And then as they move around throughout the day, they begin to use the joints,
and they're sort of squeezing the joints free of that inflammatory debris,
which then results in improvement with activity.
The easy way to remember this is to compare it against a sore throat that you might have from a viral illness.
You're well aware of the fact that when you have a sore throat from a viral illness,
and you're at the, for example, end of the illness,
when you wake up in the morning, you're coughing up a bunch of stuff,
and your throat doesn't feel well.
But then as you begin to speak and use your voice and move around, you feel much better.
And so this is the exact same problem.
If they get all this inflammation and inflammatory junk building up in the joints while they're sleeping,
and then when they wake up and begin to use the joints, it feels much better.
It's also important to note that the involvement of the joints will be symmetric.
Both joints are going to be hit by the exact same autoimmune problem.
The classic joints that are involved are the PIP joints of the fingers,
the wrists, the elbows, the ankles, and the knees.
It's important to note that the DIP is usually spared,
and that's particularly high yield because recall that in degenerative joint disease,
the PIP and the DIP were both involved.
Here's a picture of a joint from a patient with rheumatoid arthritis.
Again, remember that the hallmark is going to be the formation of the pannus,
and the pannus contains that granulation tissue, which will then contract.
And so you classically get these deformities of the joints where they get pulled one way or another,
and that's, again, because the myofibroblasts in the granulation tissue contract,
and when they contract, they then pull the joint one way or another.
Additional clinical features include joint space narrowing.
Again, as I've already mentioned, the pannus is going to contract because of the myofibroblast,
which will then narrow the joint space.
You'll get loss of cartilage, and that's because the pannus can overlie the cartilage,
and the inflammation in the pannus can destroy the cartilage.
And you can also get osteopenia,
because the inflammatory process will also begin to wear away at the bone underneath the cartilage.
Patients will also have signs of symptoms of an inflammatory process,
because, again, this is a systemic autoimmune disease,
so fever, malaise, weight loss, and myalgias will also be seen.
Other clinical features that are important, rheumatoid nodules are present.
These are nodules that usually arise in the skin, but can also be present in the visceral organs.
And they're characterized by a central area of necrosis,
which is surrounded by epithelioid histiocytes.
So rheumatoid nodules are a classic finding as well.
Vasculitis can be seen, and vasculitis can involve multiple organs.
The patient can develop a Baker's cyst, which is swelling of the bursa behind the knee,
so they can have a swollen cyst behind the knee.
And then they can develop additional systemic signs, including pleural effusions,
lymphadenopathy, which refers to enlargement of the lymph nodes,
and interstitial lung fibrosis.
The laboratory findings are particularly high yield.
The most important is that you're going to have an IgM autoantibody against the FC portion of IgG.
This is called rheumatoid factor, and it's important to note for the purposes of board exams
that it's going to be an IgM antibody against the FC portion of IgG.
And again, this is the FC portion, and that's particularly high yield.
This is called rheumatoid factor, and rheumatoid factor is actually a marker of tissue damage,
and it's also a marker of disease activity.
If you were to stick a needle in one of the joints, you would see neutrophils and high protein in the synovial fluid.
Complications of rheumatoid arthritis include anemia of chronic disease.
The idea here is that you've got a chronic inflammatory state,
and that's going to result in production of acute phase reactants, such as hepcidin.
Hepcidin will then block the ability to use iron that is stored in the macrophages,
and that will result in anemia of chronic disease.
We've covered this in detail in your red blood cell lectures.
In addition, the patients can also get secondary amyloidosis.
Recall that when you have chronic inflammation, you're going to produce, again, acute phase reactants.
One of them is a protein called SAA, which is produced by the liver.
SAA gets converted to AA, and AA will then deposit in various tissues, resulting in a secondary amyloidosis.
This is very high yield.
They like to ask this on board exams as well.
Now, seronegative spondyloarthropathies are a group of joint disorders that have a few important characteristics.
Number one, they lack rheumatoid factor, and that's what we mean by seronegative,
that the serum is negative for rheumatoid factor.
Number two, they often involve the axial skeleton, and that's what the spondyloarthropathy refers to,
the spondylo referring to the spine and the large joints of the central skeleton.
And then finally, there's often an association with HLA-B27.
The first of these disorders is called ankylosing spondyloarthritis,
and it involves the sacroiliac joints in the spine.
This classically arises in young adults, usually males, and it presents with low back pain.
Now, involvement of the vertebral spine over time can lead to fusion of the vertebra,
and that's also known as bamboo spine.
And the patients can also have uveitis, which would result in redness of the eye
and then visual abnormalities, such as blurry vision, which could eventually progress to blindness,
and then aortitis, which is inflammation of the aorta.
Now, it's important to note, especially for examinations, that when you get aortitis,
for example, here and here, that's going to result in weakening of the wall,
which will increase the risk of formation of an aneurysm.
And if were you to form an aneurysm, that could then pull on the aortic valve here and here.
And so one of the consequences of the aortitis in a patient, for example,
with ankylosing spondyloarthritis would be that they can develop aortic regurgitation
or regurgitation through the aortic valve.
The second of the seronegative spondyloarthropathies is Reiter's syndrome.
This presents as arthritis, urethritis, and conjunctivitis.
And so the classic mnemonic is can't see, can't pee, and can't climb a tree.
Now, this will usually arise in young male adults weeks after a GI or a chlamydia infection.
Psoriatic arthritis is an arthritis seen in 10% of cases of psoriasis.
It involves the axial and the peripheral joints.
And one of the key findings with involvement of the peripheral joints
is that the DIP of the hands and the feet are commonly affected.
And this results in something called a sausage finger or a sausage toe,
which is particularly high yield for board exam purposes.
The next category of arthritis is infectious arthritis.
This is arthritis due to infectious agent, usually bacterial.
The most important and most common overall cause is Neisseria gonorrhea.
This would be classically seen in a sexually active young adult.
The second most common cause is Staph aureus,
and this is classically seen in older children and adults.
Patients with an infectious arthritis will present with involvement of a single joint,
usually the knee.
The joint will be warm and erythematous with a limited range of motion.
And the patients will also have systemic signs, such as fever,
an increased wide blood cell count, and an elevated ESR.
Now, when a patient has infectious arthritis,
you want to be able to detect it quickly and treat quickly
because you can easily treat with antibiotics,
and you can then avoid any permanent damage to the joint.
The last two disorders that we're going to cover
are those that are related to deposition of crystals within the joint space,
and the first is gout.
In gout, you get deposition of monosodium urate crystals in tissues,
especially the joints,
and this monosodium urate is actually derived from uric acid,
and so it's due to hyperuricemia,
or high amounts of uric acid present within the blood.
Now, in order to understand gout,
you do need to go back to a little bit of biochemistry,
so let's do a quick overview.
Imagine that this is the lumen of the small bowel,
and this is the enterocyte that normally lines that small bowel lumen.
Now, within the diet will be DNA and RNA,
and the DNA and RNA will be broken down into purines and pyrimidines.
We're going to focus here on purines
because it's purines that lead to uric acid,
and it's uric acid that leads to gout.
So the purine breakdown products will be brought into the cell,
and they include adenosine monophosphate and guanine monophosphate.
Of course, adenine and guanine are your key purines.
Adenosine monophosphate will be broken down into hypoxanthine,
and guanine monophosphate will be broken down into guanine,
and then both of these will eventually be broken down into xanthine.
Now, xanthine will then be converted to uric acid,
and this will occur by an enzyme called xanthine oxidase,
and all of this biochemistry is particularly high yield,
and so that's why I'm illustrating it.
Now, uric acid will then be pushed into the blood,
will be filtered by the kidney,
and then will be removed from the body.
Now, of course, the key problem in gout
is that you have increased uric acid within the blood,
and that increased uric acid in the blood is called hyperuricemia,
and there's two ways by which that could occur.
That could occur by pushing too much uric acid into the blood,
or it could occur by not filtering the uric acid from the blood,
because remember that uric acid is normally excreted by the kidney,
and so this is the basic biochemical understanding
that you have to have in order to understand the disease.
So again, what we say is that gout is deposition of monosodium urate,
which is basically derived from uric acid,
so it's due to hyperuricemia.
In primary gout, which is the most common form,
we don't know what causes the hyperuricemia.
Now, when we say it's unknown,
we know that it's got to be either overproduction or decreased excretion,
and it can be both.
However, we don't know the exact cause,
and this is usually seen in adult males.
In secondary gout, we have hyperuricemia due to a known cause.
For example, it can be seen with leukemia and myeloproliferative disorders.
Now, again, in leukemia and myeloproliferative disorders,
you've got a lot of cell turnover.
The cell turnover means you're turning over a lot of nucleus,
and when you turn over a nucleus,
you're going to break down purines and pyrimidines,
and the byproduct of breakdown of purines is going to be uric acid.
So you're going to get high levels of uric acid in the blood,
which can then lead to secondary gout.
Another important cause of secondary gout is Lesch-Nihan syndrome.
Let's go back to the whiteboard to illustrate some biochemistry.
Remember that important breakdown products from the purine pathway will be AMP and GMP.
The AMP will then be broken down into hypoxanthine,
and the GMP will be broken down into guanine.
And, of course, the hypoxanthine and the guanine
can eventually result in the formation of xanthine,
and the xanthine can eventually result in the formation of uric acid.
Now, it is also possible to take these two products
and to salvage them via something called a salvage pathway
so that you can recycle them so that they don't have to then become uric acid.
Now, the key enzyme that does that is called HGPRT,
which is hypoxanthine guanine phosphoriboltransferase.
Now, look at the hypoxanthine guanine,
hypoxanthine guanine phosphoriboltransferase.
And so this enzyme allows for salvage of these two individual molecules.
Now, when you salvage these molecules,
you'll decrease the amount of xanthine,
and you'll decrease the amount of uric acid.
And so you can imagine that if a person is lacking this enzyme,
that's going to result in excess production of uric acid,
which will then result in hyperuricemia.
And so these patients with Lesch-Nihan syndrome present with gout.
However, they also have mental retardation and self-mutilation,
where they bite their lips and their fingers,
also as a complication of the high levels of uric acid.
The third cause of secondary gout would be renal insufficiency.
Now, recall that the kidney has to excrete the uric acid to get rid of it.
And so if there's insufficiency, you won't be able to excrete the uric acid.
That'll result in high levels of uric acid,
which could then result in a secondary gout.
Now, whether the patients have a high level of uric acid
because of a primary problem or a secondary problem,
the clinical findings are relatively the same.
And that is that the patients can present with acute gout.
In acute gout, you get deposition of uric acid within the joints as monosodium urate.
These crystals then trigger an acute inflammatory reaction.
It's high yield to note that the crystals activate the neutrophils.
The acute inflammation then results in painful arthritis of the great toe,
which is also known as pedagra.
Now, some of the triggers of acute gout include alcohol and consumption of meat.
When a patient consumes meat,
they're going to be bringing in a lot of RNA and DNA into the body,
which can then result in high levels of uric acid.
And when patients consume alcohol,
byproducts of alcohol can compete with uric acid at the kidney to be excreted.
And so therefore, less excretion of uric acid would occur.
And so two important triggers of acute gout are alcohol and consumption of meat.
And that's particularly high yield for the purposes of board exam.
With longstanding high levels of uric acid,
patients can develop chronic gout.
And the hallmark of chronic gout is the formation of TOFI.
TOFI are white chalky aggregates of uric acid crystals in soft tissue or joints.
And often it's associated with fibrosis in a giant cell reaction.
In addition, in chronic gout, patients can develop renal failure.
And that's because uric acid can actually deposit within the tubules of the kidney,
damaging the kidney.
Here's a picture of TOFI.
These are white chalky deposits of uric acid crystals within the soft tissue, for example.
And remember that you get fibrosis surrounding these white chalky deposits.
Laboratory findings in patients with gout will be hyperuricemia.
Of course, it's due to a high level of uric acid in the blood.
And in addition, sampling of the synovial fluid will show needle-shaped crystals
with negative birefringents under polarized light.
Very high yield to know that these are needle-shaped crystals.
And it's also high yield to know that they are negatively birefringent under polarized light.
Now, board examiners like you to know what is meant by negative birefringents.
And basically what it means is that when the crystals lay flat, they're yellow.
And so the way I remember this is that when they lay low, they're yellow.
And so that's an important thing to be aware of.
Board examiners could also ask you what color are the crystals under parallel light.
And the answer is yellow.
And that's easy to remember because there's two L's in both yellow and parallel.
The final disorder is pseudogout.
This clinically resembles gout.
However, it's not gout, hence the word pseudo.
Instead of being due to deposition of monosodium urate,
it's due to deposition of calcium pyrophosphate.
When you stick a needle in the joint and you take the synovial fluid,
you will see rhomboid-shaped crystals instead of the needle-shaped crystals.
And there will be weak positive birefringents under polarized light.
And that concludes our discussion of joint.